<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be enquired of in the diocesse of Carlile, in the visitation of the reuerend father in God, Francis, Lord Bishop of Carlile</title>
            <author>Church of England. Diocese of Carlisle. Bishop (1626-1629 : White)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00167</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10172.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2634</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24401353</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24401353</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27636</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00167)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27636)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1850:75)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be enquired of in the diocesse of Carlile, in the visitation of the reuerend father in God, Francis, Lord Bishop of Carlile</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Diocese of Carlisle. Bishop (1626-1629 : White)</author>
                  <author>White, Francis, 1564?-1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[G. Purslowe],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Anno Dom. [blank] &amp; Consecrationis suæ [blank]".</note>
                  <note>Publisher suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27636:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27636:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES TO BE ENQVIRED <hi>OF IN THE DIOCESSE OF</hi> CARLILE, in the Viſitation of <hi>the Reuerend Father in God,</hi> Francis, Lord Biſhop of <hi>Carlile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Dom. &amp; Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis ſuae</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London. 1627.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="oath">
            <pb facs="tcp:27636:2"/>
            <head>The forme of the Oath to be miniſtred vnto the Church-wardens and Side-men.</head>
            <p>YOu ſhall ſweare, that you, and euery of you, ſhall duely conſider, and diligently enquire of all and euery of theſe Articles giuen you in charge; and that all affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, fauour, hope of reward and gaine, or feare of diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or malice ſet aſide, you ſhall preſent all and euery ſuch perſon of or within your Pariſh, as hath committed any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, or made any default mentioned in theſe, or any of theſe Articles; or which are vehemently ſuſpected or defamed of any ſuch offence or default: Wherein you ſhal deale vprightly and fully; neither preſenting, nor ſparing to preſent any, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to truth: hauing in this action God before your eyes, with an earneſt zeale to maintaine truth and vertue, and to ſuppreſse vice. So helpe you God, and the holy contents of this Booke.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles_of_visitation">
            <pb facs="tcp:27636:2"/>
            <head>ARTICLES TO BE <hi>EN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of in the Dioceſſe of</hi> Carlile, ANNO DOM.</head>
            <div type="articles">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Titul." n="1"/>
               <head>Articles concerning Religion and Doctrine.</head>
               <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether bee there any abiding in,<note place="margin">Hereticall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions.</note> or reſorting to your Pariſh, that haue wilfully maintained and defended any hereſies, errors, or falſe opinions, contrary to the faith of Chriſt, and holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Jtem,</hi> Whether doth any in your Pariſh,<note place="margin">Abſence from Church.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 16. yeers of age or vpwards, or others lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or commonly reſorting to any houſe in your pariſh, wilfully ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent themſelues from your pariſh Church, Chappell, or Oratorie, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sundayes and holidaies, and other daies appointed, at Morning and Euening prayers? Or who come late to Church and depart from Church before diuine Seruice and Sermon be ended? Or whether be there any, that perſwade others to forbeare or abſtaine comming to Church, to heare diuine Seruice, and receiue the holy Communion according to his Maieſties lawes in that behalfe enacted?</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Jtem,</hi> Whether be there any in your pariſh, that hath beene,<note place="margin">Vnlawfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticles.</note> or is vehemently ſuſpected to haue beene preſent at any vnlawfull aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, conuenticles, or meetings, vnder colour or pretence of any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Religion; or doth any affirme and maintaine ſuch meetings to be lawfull, contrarie to his Maieſties ſtatutes in that behalfe?</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether be there any within your pariſh, that deny,<note place="margin">Impugners of the Kings Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie.</note> or perſwade any to deny, withſtand and impugne the Kings Maieſties authority and Supremacie in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall within his Realme?</p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>Jtem,</hi> Whether be there any abiding in,<note place="margin">Popiſh Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants.</note> or reſorting to your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, that be, or are commonly reputed or taken to bee Recuſant Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,
<pb facs="tcp:27636:3"/>
refuſing to repaire to the Church to heare diuine Seruice, and receiue the holy Communion, and being diſobedient to his Highneſſe Lawes in that behalfe prouided? Or doe any publiſh, fell, or diſperſe any ſuperſtitious books or writings; or other books, libels, or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of any lectuaries, touching the Religion, State, or Eccleſiaſticall gouermnent of this Kingdome of England? Preſent their names, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and conditions. Doth any Papiſt keepe a Schoolemaſter in his houſe, which commeth not to Church, as is required? What is his name, and how long hath he taught there or elſe-where?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Titul." n="2"/>
               <head>Articles concerning Publique Prayer and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacraments.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">deprauing the Booke of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer, &amp; Ceremonies.</note>FIrſt, Whether hath any of your pariſh ſpoken, or declared any thing in the derogation, or deprauing of the forme of Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the Church of England, &amp; Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, Rites and Ceremonies, ſet forth and preſcribed in the Booke of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer, by the Kings Maieſtie authoriſed and confirmed? Doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny preach, ſpeake, or declare, that it containeth any thing which is not agreeable to the holy Scriptures?</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">Perſwading a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Miniſter to alter the form of common Prayer.</note>2 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether hath any in your pariſh cauſed, procured, or maintained any Miniſter to ſay any common or publike prayer, or to adminiſter either of the Sacraments of Baptiſme and the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, otherwiſe, or in any other manner and forme, then is mentioned in the ſaid book of Common Prayer: Or whether hath any interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, hindred, let, or diſturbed the Miniſter to reade diuine Seruice, and adminiſter the Sacraments, in ſuch manner and forme as is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the ſaid booke, or interrupted him in his preaching and Sermons?</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">Obſeruation of the forme of Baptiſme, and Croſſe.</note>3 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is the Sacrament of Baptiſme rightly and duly adminiſtred, according to the preſcript Forme expreſſed in the booke of Common Prayer, with due obſeruations of all Rites and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies preſcribed in the adminiſtration of the ſame, without adding, or altering any part or parcell of any prayers, interrogatories, or not v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ſigne of the Croſſe in the adminiſtration of the ſame?<note place="margin">Children refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, or dying without Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. Parents of children ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is the Sacrament of Baptiſme refuſed to bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred to any children borne in or out of wedlocke, their birth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made knowne vnto the Miniſter of the pariſh, and offered to him to be baptized; or haue any ſuch children dyed vn-baptized?</p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>Jtem,</hi> Whether be the Parents of any child to bee baptized, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to be Godfathers and Godmothers to the ſame?</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27636:3"/>6 <hi>Item,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Priuate Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme.</note> Whether haue there any children beene baptized in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate houſes, by any Lay perſon, or Midwife, or Popiſh Prieſt, or by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Miniſter, but vpon vrgent occaſion, when the child was in danger of death?</p>
               <p n="7">7 <hi>Jtem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Baptizing Papiſts chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren.</note> Whether haue the children which haue beene borne to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Popiſh Recuſants, or begotten by them in your pariſh, beene pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely baptized in your pariſh Church, by your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate; or by whom were they baptized, or where to your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge?</p>
               <p n="8">8 <hi>Jtem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Receiuing the Lords S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per thrice a yeere.</note> Whether hath the bleſſed Sacrament of the Lords Supper beene duely and reuerently adminiſtred euery moneth, or thrice eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yeere at leaſt, whereof once at Eaſter, within your pariſh Church, to euery pariſhioner being of ſixteene yeeres of age, or vpwards?</p>
               <p n="9">9 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is the ſaid holy Sacrament deliuered vnto,<note place="margin">Kneeling a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</note> or receiued by any of the Communicants within your pariſh, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuerently ſit or ſtand, or doe not deuoutly and humbly kneele vpon their knees?</p>
               <p n="10">10 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether hath any of your pariſh,<note place="margin">Notorious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Communio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> which bee openly knowne to liue in notorious ſinne without repentance, or excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate perſons, or Schiſmaticks, common and notorious deprauers of the Religion and gouernment of this Realme, without vnfaigned ſorrow ſhowne for their impiety and wickedneſſe, beene admitted to be partaker of the ſaid holy Communion?</p>
               <p n="11">11 <hi>Jtem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Debarring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers with cauſe.</note> Whether hath any of your pariſh beene debarred from the ſaid holy Communion, without iuſt cauſe, and without intimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on firſt giuen to the Ordinary or Biſhop of the Dioceſſe: and by whoſe default?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Titul." n="3"/>
               <head>Articles concerning the Church, the Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thereof, and the Churches Poſſeſſions.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, Whether haue you in your Church or Chappell,<note place="margin">Books and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naments in the Church</note> the whole Bible of the largeſt Volumne, and of the laſt tranſlation, the booke of Common Prayer, lately ſet forth by his Maieſties authoritie, the two bookes of Homilies, and Biſhop Iewels Apologie, all well and fairely bound: a Font of ſtone ſet vp in the ancient vſuall place: A conuenient and decent Communion Table, with a Carpet of ſilke or ſome other decent ſtuffe, continually laid vpon the Table at time of diuine Seruice,<note place="margin">Abuſing of Communio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Table.</note> and a faire linnen cloath at the time of adminiſtring the Communion: And whether is the ſame Table placed conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
<pb facs="tcp:27636:4"/>
as it ought: And whether is it ſo vſed in or out of time of diuine Seruice or Sermon, as is not agreeable to the holy vſe of it; as by ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on it, and by throwing hats on it, or writing on it; or is it abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to other prophaner vſes? Are the tenne commandements ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Eaſt end of your Church, with other ſentences of Scripture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout?</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ings apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ning to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urches.</note>2 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether haue you in your ſaid Church or Chappell, a conuenient ſeate for your Miniſter to reade diuine Seruice in, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a comely Pulpit ſet vp in a conuenient place, with a decent cloth or Cuſhion for the ſame; a comely, large and fine Surplice; a faire Communion Cup, a Flagon of Siluer or Pewter, with all other things and ornaments neceſſary for the celebration of diuine Seruice, and adminiſtration of the Sacraments: and whether haue you a Cheſt for Almes, with three locks and keyes and another Cheſt for keeping the Bookes and Ornaments of the Church, and the Regiſter Booke? Haue you a Regiſter Booke in Parchment,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>giſter book.</note> for Chriſtenings, Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and burials, and is the ſame kept in all points according to the Canons? And haue you a Table ſet in your Church, of the degrees wherein by law men are prohibited to marry?</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>parations Churches, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d Parſonage uſes.</note>3 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is your Church or Chappell, with the Chauncell thereof, and your Parſonage or Vicarage houſe, in good reparations; if any be ruinated and waſted, in whom is the default? Is your Church, Chancell and Chappell, decently and comely kept, aſwell within as without; and be the ſeates well maintained, the Steeple and Bells preſerued; the windowes well glazed; the floore kept paued, plaine and euen,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>eping clean Churches.</note> and all things in orderly and decent ſort, without duſt, or any thing that may be either noyſome or vnſeemely for the houſe of God, as is preſcribed in the 85. Canon?</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ncing and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>eping the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>hurchyard.</note>4 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether be your Churchyards well fenced, and kept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out abuſe; if not, whoſe default is it: hath any perſon encroached vpon the ground of the Churchyard: Hath any vſed a place conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to holy vſe prophanely or wickedly: haue any quarrelled or ſtricken another in Church or Churchyard:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ophaning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d annoying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rd.</note> haue any annoyed your Churchyard, or the fence thereof, by putting in of Cattell, by hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of clothes, or by laying there any duſt, dung, or other filthineſſe?</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hurches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>acant.</note>5 <hi>Item,</hi> whether is your Church full, or vacant of an incumbent; if vacant, who receiueth the fruits thereof, and who ſerueth the Cure, and by what authoritie? And whether is it a Parſonage, Vicaridge, or Donatiue, or Appropriation?</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <note place="margin">oncealing of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hurch goods.</note>6 <hi>Item,</hi> What legacies haue beene giuen to the vſe and benefit of
<pb facs="tcp:27636:4"/>
your Church; how haue they beene beſtowed; who receiued them, and detaineth them without due imployment? Doth any detaine or embezell any of the Church goods, or any other gifts giuen to chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vſes?</p>
               <p n="7">7 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether hath any in your pariſh defaced,<note place="margin">Defacing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſeemely or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments. Burying of P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſh Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants.</note> or cauſed to bee defaced, any monuments or ornaments in your Church?</p>
               <p n="8">8 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether hath any Popiſh Recuſant, being lawfully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, beene enterred or buried in your Church or Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, before abſolution of that cenſure and excommunication? If yea, then by whom and when?</p>
               <p n="9">9 <hi>Jtem,</hi> Whether be not the profits, tithes,<note place="margin">Alienation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tithes and profits of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Church.</note> and other commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Eccleſiaſticall, impiouſly and wickedly, to the diſhonour of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, and preiudice of the ſacred Miniſterie, conuerted to the vſe and benefit of couetous Patrons, and by them receiued and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and how long haue they beene ſo vſed to your knowledge?</p>
               <p n="10">10 <hi>Jtem,</hi> Whether haue you the Terrier of all the gleab-lands,<note place="margin">A Terrier o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Glebe lands and other poſſeſsions the Church.</note> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, gardens, orchyards, houſes, ſtocks, implements, tenements, and portions of tithes (whether within your pariſh or without) belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your Parſonage or Vicaridge, taken by the view of honeſt men in your ſaid pariſh; and whether the ſaid Terrier be laid vp in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Regiſtrie, and in whoſe hands are any of them now? And if you haue no Terrier already made in Parchment, you the Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and Side-men, together with your Parſon or Vicar, or in his abſence, your Curate, are to make diligent enquiry, and preſentment of the premiſes, and make, ſubſcribe, and ſigne the ſaid Terrier, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Titul." n="4"/>
               <head>Articles concerning Miniſters, and Preachers of Gods holy Word.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, Whether is your Miniſter, Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, <note place="margin">Degrees of Miniſters.</note> a gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate in either of the Vniuerſities, or no: if yea, then of what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree? Is hee a publike Preacher of Gods word and by whom is hee ſo licenſed?</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether doth your Miniſter diſtinctly, and reuerently ſay Diuine Seruice vpon Sundayes and Holidayes,<note place="margin">Obſeruation of the forme and time of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> &amp; other dayes appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be obſerued by the booke of Common Prayer, as Wedneſdaies and Fridaies, and the Eues of euery Sunday and Holiday, at fit and vſuall times And doth your Miniſter duly obſerue the orders, Rites, and Ceremonies preſcr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bed in the ſaid Booke of Common Prayer, as well in reading all publique praiers, and the Letanie, as alſo in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring the Sacraments, ſolemnization of Matrimonie, viſitation of
<pb facs="tcp:27636:5"/>
the ſicke burying the dead, churching of women, and all other like Rites and offices of the Church, in ſuch maner &amp; forme, as in the ſaid booke of common prayer is enioyned, without omiſsion or addition of any thing: And doth he read the Booke of the laſt Canons yeerely?</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ontinuall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ating of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>rplice.</note>3 <hi>Jtem,</hi> whether doth your Miniſter, both morning and euening, reading diuine Seruice, and adminiſtring the Sacraments, and other Rites of the Church, weare the Surplice, according to the Canons: And doth he neuer omit wearing of the ſame at ſuch times?</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bſeruation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Rites.</note>4 <hi>Jtem,</hi> Whether doth your Miniſter bid holidayes and faſting-daies, as is appointed? Doth he adminiſter the holy Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion euery moneth; or thrice in the yere at leaſt, whereof once at Eaſter, to euery pariſhioner: doth he receiue the ſame himſelfe on euery day that hee adminiſtreth it to others, and vſeth the words of Inſtitution accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the booke, without alteration, at euery time that the bread and wine is renewed? Doth he vſe and neuer omit the ſigne of the Croſſe in baptiſme, or doth he euer baptize in any Baſon or other thing but the vſuall Font? Doth he marry without a Ring, or in times prohibited, or without the banes thrice publiſhed, without a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Licence from the Arch-biſhop, or Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, or his Chancellor, firſt had and obtained?</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reachers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ithout <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cence.</note>5 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is your Miniſter a Preacher licenſed or no? If no, whether doth he take vpon him, in his own Cure, or elſe-where, to expound any Scripture or matter of doctrine, and doth not keepe himſelfe to the reading of Homilies publiſhed by Authoritie? And if he be licenſed, doth he preach vſually according to the 45. Canon, in his owne cure, or ſome other neighbour Church, where no Preacher is: doth he preach ſtanding, and with his hat off? Or whether doth hee or his Curate,<note place="margin">Reading Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>here is no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ermon.</note> vpon euery Sunday when there is no Sermon, reade an Homily, or ſome part thereof, according as hee ought to doe?</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <note place="margin">Preaching of falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, &amp; new opinions.</note>6 <hi>Jtem,</hi> Whether doth your Miniſter publiſh in his Sermon any doctrine which is new and ſtrange, and diſagreeing from the Word of God, and from the Articles of Chriſtian faith and religion, agreed on and publiſhed, <hi>Ann. Dom.</hi> 1562. or whether doe they teach any thing, which they would haue the people rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>giouſly to obſerue and beleeue, but that which is agreeable to the Scriptures, and that which the Catholike Fathers and ancient Biſhops haue gathered out of that doctrine, according to the Canon?</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <note place="margin">Names of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>trangers to be taken.</note>7 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether are any Miniſters admitted to preach in your Church, who doe not, before the Churchwardens, ſubſcribe their
<pb facs="tcp:27636:5"/>
names in your booke for that purpoſe, the day when hee preached, and the name of the Biſhop of whom he had licence to preach? And is any one admitted to preach, before he ſheweth his licence?</p>
               <p n="8">8 <hi>Item,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Oppoſition of Preachers in their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</note> Doth any Preacher in your Pulpit particularly impugne and confute any doctrine deliuered by others his fellow Preachers, before he hath acquainted the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe therewith, and receiued order from him, what to doe in that caſe?</p>
               <p n="9">9 <hi>Jtem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Praying for his Maieſtie, &amp;c.</note> Doth your Miniſter vſe alwayes to pray for the Kings Maieſtie, the Queene, Clergie, Councell, &amp;c. giuing them their full titles, as in the Canon is required?</p>
               <p n="10">10 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is your Miniſter reſident vpon his Benefice,<note place="margin">Non reſidence of the Miniſter</note> or abſent; if abſent, by whom is the Cure ſerued, the fruits receiued? Doth your Miniſter or Curate ſerue any more Cures then one? If yea, then what other Cure doth he ſerue, and how farre are they diſtant?</p>
               <p n="11">11 <hi>Jtem,</hi> Whether doth he catechize the youth of his pariſh vpon Sundaies and holidaies before Euening prayer, for halfe an houre,<note place="margin">Catechizing.</note> or more, in the Catechiſme ſet forth in the booke of common prayer: and whether doe all the pariſhioners diligently attend his catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing? and who refuſe to ſend their children and ſeruants to be cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chized by him?</p>
               <p n="12">12 <hi>Item,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Miniſters to call for reliefe of the poore, and almes-deeds. Symonie.</note> Doth your Miniſter carefully looke to the reliefe of the poore, and from time to time call vpon his pariſhioners, to giue ſomewhat according to their ability, to godly and charitable vſes, eſpecially when they make their wills?</p>
               <p n="13">13 <hi>Jtem,</hi> whether is your Miniſter ſuſpected or knowne to haue obtained his Benefice, or ſpirituall promotion, by any ſymoniacall compact, directly or indirectly?</p>
               <p n="14">14 <hi>Item,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Demiſing of Benefices.</note> Whether doth your Miniſter demiſe the profits of his Benefice to any Lay-man, aboue one yeere, and is not reſident there; &amp; keepeth no hoſpitality vpon his Benefice being of ſufficient value?</p>
               <p n="15">15 <hi>Item,</hi> Doth your Miniſter, in the Rogation dayes,<note place="margin">Obſeruing of Rogation weeke.</note> goe in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ambulation of the circuit of the pariſh, ſaying and vſing the prayers, ſuffrages, and thanksgiuing to God, appointed by law, according to his dutie, thanking God for his bleſsings, and praying for his grace and fauour?</p>
               <p n="16">16 <hi>Jtem,</hi> What Curates or Preachers doe reade prayers,<note place="margin">Curates not licenſed, and Lay-men do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing offices of Miniſter.</note> or admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the Sacraments in your pariſh, without lawfull licence from the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, vnder his hand and ſeale, according to the Canon: or doth any Lay-man, not hauing holy orders, preſume to reade publike prayers in the Church?</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27636:6"/>
                  <note place="margin">Lectures and Preachers to read Seruice.</note>17 <hi>Jtem,</hi> Whether haue you any Preacher or Lecturer in your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and whether (if any ſuch be) he doth twice at the leaſt euery yere reade himſelfe diuine Seruice both morning and euening two ſeueral Sundaies publikely in his Surplice; and alſo twice in the yeere admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter both the Sacraments, with ſuch rites and ceremonies as are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the book of commom prayer, according to the 56. Canon?</p>
               <p n="18">
                  <note place="margin">Conuerſation of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</note>18 <hi>Jtem,</hi> Whether is your Miniſter ſtudious in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and abſtaineth from mechanicall trades, or labour not be fitting his function, and from apparell vnſeemely for his calling, and from gaming,<note place="margin">Miniſters for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking their calling.</note> ſwearing and drunkennes, or ſuch notorious crimes: or is there any in your pariſh, who hauing beene admitted into holy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, either Deacon or Miniſter, doth relinquiſh and forſake his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and liueth in the courſe of his life as a Lay-man?</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <note place="margin">Miniſters re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealing pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</note>19 <hi>Jtem,</hi> Whether doth your Miniſter before the ſeuerall times of the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, admoniſh and exhort his pariſhioners, if they haue their conſciences troubled and diſquieted, to reſort vnto him, or ſome other learned Miniſter, and open his griefe, that he may receiue ſuch ghoſtly counſell and comfort, as his conſcience may be relieued, and by the Miniſter he may receiue the benefit of abſolution, to the quiet of his conſcience, and auoyding of the ſcruple; And if any man confeſſe his ſecret &amp; hidden ſinnes being ſick or whole, to the Miniſter, for the vnburthening of his conſcience, and receiuing ſuch ſpirituall conſolation, doth or hath the ſaid Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter at any time reuealed and made knowne to any perſon whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, any crime or offence ſo committed to his truſt and ſecrecie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the 113. Canon?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Titul." n="5"/>
               <head>Articles concerning Matrimony.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, <note place="margin">Marriage within Leuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call degrees.</note> Whether be there any in your pariſh, that haue married with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the degrees of affinity or conſanguinity by the Law of God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden? If any, what be they?</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether haue any beene married ſecretly in priuate hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <note place="margin">Priuate mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</note> or without their parents or gouernours conſent ſignified, being vnder the age of 21. yeeres?</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether doe any perſons lawfully married, <note place="margin">Married per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons liuing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>part.</note> liue aſunder vnlawfully, and in whom is the default?</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Item,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Marriage without banes and licence.</note> Whether any perſons (the banes beeing not thrice publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the Church) haue beene married without licence; who were preſent at ſuch marriages, and what Miniſter married them?</p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>Jtem,</hi> Whether any perſons by licence or without, <note place="margin">Perſons mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out of their Pariſhes.</note> haue bin mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in your pariſh Church, neither of them at that time dwelling in your ſaid pariſh?</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27636:6"/>6 <hi>Item,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Recuſants marriage.</note> What Popiſh Recuſants or their children haue beene mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in your Pariſh, in what ſort was that matrimonie ſolemnized; when, and by whom?</p>
               <p n="7">7 <hi>Item,</hi> Is there any in your Pariſh, that is voyced, noted,<note place="margin">Bigamy.</note> and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly reported and accuſed to haue two wiues liuing, or two huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Titul." n="6"/>
               <head>Articles concerning the Churchwardens.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, Whether be the Churchwardens choſen by the Miniſter and Pariſhioners, according to the 89. Canon;<note place="margin">Election of Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens.</note> and whether hath any taken vpon him to be Church-warden, being not ſo choſen: or hath any continued aboue one yeere in his office without a new choice?</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Jtem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens due ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</note> Whether haue any Churchwardens deteined any of the Church goods, and not made a iuſt account of what they haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and expended?</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Item,</hi> Haue they beene, and are they diligent in their office,<note place="margin">Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens diligent in the Church</note> to ſee decencie kept in the Church, and order in the time of Common Prayer, and adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and that there bee no diſturbance, but ſoberneſſe and quietneſſe in the Church?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Titul." n="7"/>
               <head>Articles concerning the Pariſhioners.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, Whether doe any in your Pariſh prophane the Sunday by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull games, drinking or tippling,<note place="margin">Prophaning the Lords day.</note> eſpecially in the time of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer, or Sermon: or by working, and doing the ordinary workes of their vocations and trades?</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Item,</hi> Is there any in your Pariſh,<note place="margin">Impugne the Rites and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the Church.</note> that do impugne or ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Rites and Ceremonies of the Church of England, or the lawfull vſe of them; and the gouernment of this Church vnder his Maieſtie by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, and other Eccleſiaſticall Officers?</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Item,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuerent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour at di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uine Seruice.</note> Who in your pariſh doe come to the Sermon only and not to diuine Seruice; and who do not reuerently behaue themſelues du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of diuine Seruice, deuoutly kneeling when the generall Confeſsion of ſinnes, the Letany, the tenne Commandements, and all Prayers and Collects are read: and vſing all duly and lowly reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence when the bleſſed Name of the Lord <hi>Ieſus</hi> is mentioned, and ſtanding vp when the Articles of the Beliefe, the <hi>Magnificat, Nunc dimittis,</hi> the <hi>Te Deum, Benedictus,</hi> and <hi>Gloria Patri, &amp;c.</hi> are read, or who doe couer their heads in the Church, during the whole time of diuine Seruice, vnleſſe it be in caſe of neceſsity; in which caſe they may weare a nightcap? Or who do giue themſelues to babbling, tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, or walking, and are not attentiue to heare the Word read and preached?</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27636:7"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eauing their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wn Churches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o goe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hers.</note>4 <hi>Item,</hi> Is there any of your Pariſh, hauing a Preacher to their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, that doe abſent themſelues from his Sermons, and reſort to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places to heare other Preachers: or doe any in your Pariſh com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, or baptize their children in any other Pariſh?</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <note place="margin">Exception a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter. Churching of Women.</note>5 <hi>Item,</hi> Is there any in your pariſh, that refuſe to haue their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren baptized, or themſelues to receiue the Communion of your Miniſter, taking exception againſt him? or haue any wiues refuſed to come to Church, according to the Booke of Common Prayer, to giue thanks to God for their ſafe deliuerance, in a decent habit, as hath beene anciently accuſtomed?</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <note place="margin">Diſgracing of Miniſters.</note>6 <hi>Item,</hi> Hath any in your pariſh ſpoken ſlanderous and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full words againſt your Miniſter, to the ſcandall of his vocation; or againſt their marriage or wiues, againſt his neighbour, defaming them touching any crime of Eccleſiaſticall cognizance?</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <note place="margin">Opening of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hops vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olidaies.</note>7 <hi>Jtem,</hi> Whether doe any in your Pariſh exerciſe any trade or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, buy or ſell, or keepe open ſhops, or ſet out any wares to be ſold, vpon Sundaies and Holidayes, by themſelues, their ſeruants, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices, or haue otherwiſe prophaned the ſaid dayes?</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <note place="margin">Keeping holy of the 5. of Auguſt, and the 5. of Nouember.</note> 8 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is the 5. of Auguſt, and the 5. of Nouember kept holy, and thanksgiuing made to God, according to the order ſet forth in that behalfe?</p>
               <p n="9">9 <hi>Jtem,</hi> Is there any in your Pariſh, that bee, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dultery, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ication, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt, &amp;c.</note> or are commonly knowne or reputed to bee blaſphemers of Gods holy Name, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, adulterers, fornicators, inceſtuous perſons, concealers or har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers of fornicators or adulterers: haue any beene detected of ſuch notorious crimes, and what penance haue they done for the ſame?</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <note place="margin">Commutation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f penance.</note>10 <hi>Jtem,</hi> What corporall puniſhments for any ſuch offences, haue beene commuted and changed into a pecuniary mulct or ſumme of money by any Eccleſiaſticall Iudge exerciſing iuriſdiction within this Dioceſſe, by vertue of any graunt or Commiſsion; or what was the ſumme of money by them or any of them ſo receiued and taken, and to what vſes was the ſame beſtowed: or whether vpon ſome commutations, was the vnfaigned repentance of the delinquent pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in the Church?</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <note place="margin">Perſons dying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce the 2. of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ebr. 1626.</note>11 <hi>Item,</hi> What perſon or perſons haue died &amp; departed this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall life, ſince the 2. day of February laſt paſt, and whether did they make any laſt wills or Teſtaments, and who were their executors, or whether died they inteſtate, and who hath the adminiſtration of their goods; and what be the names of ſuch deceaſed, and executors, and adminiſtrators.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27636:7"/>12 <hi>Item,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Adminiſtring of goods with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out authoritie.</note> Whether haue any in your pariſh adminiſtred the goods of any perſon deceaſed, without lawfull authoritie, and before he or they haue proued the wil or Teſtament of the party deceaſed, or haue obtained Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſsion from the Ordinary, to diſpoſe the ſaid mouable goods; or are there any wills vnproued, or goods not adminiſtred?</p>
               <p n="13">13 <hi>Item,</hi> What perſons be excommunicate within your Pariſh,<note place="margin">Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate perſons.</note> and for what cauſe to your knowledge: and whether do any of them repaire to the Church, in time of Prayer vnabſolued.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Titul." n="8"/>
               <head>Articles concerning Schoolemaſters, Phyſicians, and Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, and Pariſh Clarks.</head>
               <p>FIrſt,<note place="margin">Schoolema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenced.</note> is there any Schoolemaſter in your Pariſh that teacheth pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely or priuately, not licenſed by the Ordinarie, or the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe? Doth hee teach any Papiſts or Sectaries children, that come not to Church?<note place="margin">Duty of all Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters.</note> And doth he inſtruct all his ſchollers to learne the ſhorter Catechiſme by the lawe eſtabiſhed, contained in the booke of common Prayer? Is he a graduate, &amp; ſufficient to teach?</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Item,</hi> What Phyſician or Chyrurgion is in your pariſh vnlicenſed,<note place="margin">Phyſicians no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> licenced.</note> and beeing not a Doctor of Phyſicke in either of the Vniuerſities, doth practiſe phyſike? And what ignorant perſons haue left their trade, and taken vpon them to profeſſe Phyſicke or Chyrurgery; and who be they that ſo abuſe the people?</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Item,</hi> Haue you a fit pariſh-Clarke, aged 20. yeeres at leaſt,<note place="margin">Pariſh Clarks</note> of honeſt life, able to reade and write? Are his and the Sextons wages paid without fraud? if not, then whoſe default is it? by whom is hee choſen: is he diligent in his office, and ſeruiceable to the Miniſter; doth he meddle with any thing aboue his Office; doth he keepe the Church cleane, the doores locked? Is any thing loſt and ſpoiled by his default, and doth he execute his office dulie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Titul." n="9"/>
               <head>Articles concerning Eccleſiaſticall offices.</head>
               <p>FIrſt,<note place="margin">Exceſſiue fees.</note> Whether be there any eccleſiaſticall officers that exerciſe ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical iuriſdiction within this Dioceſſe that take and receiue, or exact any extraordinary and exceſſiue fees for any cauſe. Whether haue your Churchwardens and Queſtmen concealed any abuſes or offences puniſhable in the Eccleſiaſticall Court; and whether ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences being preſented, are ſuppreſſed and vnpuniſhed?</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Item,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Table of fees in Courts.</note> Whether is there not a Table of Fees in euery Court of the Conſiſtorie, Archdeacons, and Commiſſaries, allowed and ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by the Iudge and Regiſter of the Court of Conſiſtory, <hi>Ann. Dom.</hi> 1597. and the ſame euery Court day hung vp in ſome publike place of the Court and Regiſtry?</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27636:8"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eeding of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cts without Notarie.</note>3 <hi>Item,</hi> Doth any Eccleſiaſticall Iudge ſpeed any act in any cauſe priuately of himſelfe, and not in preſence of ſome publike Notarie or Actuarie?</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>buſes in Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aritors and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umners.</note>4 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether is there any exceſsiue number of Apparitors and Sumners in this Dioceſſe; or haue any of them, vnder pretence of authoritie, cited and ſummoned any perſon vnlawfully, or hath taken any reward for the concealing of any offence or ſinne, or the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyding of puniſhment of the offenders; and who be they that haue done ſo; or do they take any fees not accuſtomable? haue they threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned any to proſecute them, if they had no reward? and do they ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon any, without a Citation firſt had?</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <note place="margin">Abuſes in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall offices.</note>5 <hi>Jtem,</hi> Hath any Eccleſiaſticall Iudge, or Officer, Aduocate, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter, Procter, Clarks, or other ſuch miniſters any way abuſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in their offices, contrary to the Law and Canons in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe prouided?</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <note place="margin">Sincerity and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mpartiality <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors.</note>6 <hi>Item,</hi> Laſtly, Whether haue you and euery of you, ſincerely, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly, and without any impartiall affection and concealing, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented and made knowne all and euery the offenders, in any of the matters mentioned in the precedent Articles exhibited vnto you, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as they are taken in truth to be, or by common fame reported?</p>
               <p>If you know of any other default or crime of Eccleſiaſticall cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance, you are to preſent the ſame.</p>
               <p>The Miniſters of euery pariſh may ioyne in preſentment with the Churchwardens and Side-men: and if they will not preſent, then the Miniſters themſelues (being the perſons that ſhould haue the chiefe care for the ſuppreſsing of ſinne and impiety in their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes) may preſent the crimes aforeſaid, and ſuch things as ſhall be thought to require due reformation. <hi>Can.</hi> 113.</p>
               <p>There muſt be ſeuerall preſentments made to euery ſeuerall Article.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Hos Articulos ſub hiſce Titulis in hac viſitatione, proponit inquirendos,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>FRANCIS. CARLIL.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:27636:8"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
